<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An argument wherin the apparaile of women is both reproued and defended</title>
            <title>Ab urbe condita. Selections. English. 1551.</title>
            <author>Livy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1534</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16612A.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33142603</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33142603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1881:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An argument wherin the apparaile of women is both reproued and defended</title>
                  <title>Ab urbe condita. Selections. English. 1551.</title>
                  <author>Livy.</author>
                  <author>Thomas, William, d. 1554.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the house of Thomas Berthelet Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Jmprinted at London in Fletestrete :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno MDLI [1551]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Place and publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸, D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Translation attributed to William Thomas.  Cf. ODNB.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border (McK. &amp; F. 30[alpha]), has date 1534 in sill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clothing and dress --  Social aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Roman women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sumptuary laws --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:1"/>
                  <p>An Argument, wherin the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raile of women is both reproued and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. ❀</p>
                  <p>ANNO MDLI.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
                     <p>1534</p>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:2"/>
                  <head>The printer to the reder.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He gentilwoman, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hath cauſed this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be printed, happened a litle before Shroftetide, to be at a bidden feaſt in London, in companie of dyuers gentle men and gentle women: where emongeſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther talke, firſt of the baſeneſſe of our coyne, and afterwardes of exceſſe in apparayle (whiche are the common talkes of theſe daies:) One of the companie beganne to make muche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dooe againſt women, for laiyng out their heare, for wearyng of verdin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales, for bonne graces, for ſilkes, and .xx. other thynges. Wherin it ſeemed to this gentle woman, he vſed not that temperance, that his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and lernyng required. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe mildely anſwered: that ſeus God hath created the thynges of this
<pb facs="tcp:28147:3"/>
worlde for the ſeruice of man, and not man for them: ſhe thought, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as well as men, myght vſe the ſame faire thynges of this worlde in their apparaile, which without ſome facion woulde bee vnſeemely. And lyke as their heare, or ſuche other, was a beautie, whiche beyng coupled with honeſtie, maketh the perſon the more acceptable: ſo beeyng coupled with the contrary, it diſgraceth and maketh theim the more lothſome. Wherfore the thyng beyng ſo indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, if it ſhoulde not be laufull for them that be honeſt, to be clenly and fayre, it might folow, that the other ſort ſhoulde be more ſet by than thei: and ſo ſhould honeſtie decaie. In dede (ſaied ſhe) if you coulde bryng men as well to reforme their hertes, as ye woulde haue women doe their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraile, ye ſhoulde neuer nede thus to braule with vs. Whervpon the man
<pb facs="tcp:28147:3"/>
waxed ſomewhat warme in agraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng the mattier, and (by a maner of raylyng) after many ſentences of ſcripture alleged, he fell into an ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that <hi>Cato</hi> made againſt the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of women, and ſo handled the matter, that it ſeemed he had put all men to ſilence: in ſuche wiſe as for a good ſpace, no man ſpake a woorde. At laſt maiſter William Thomas, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in the company, began to ſaie. This is muche like the nonnes leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that whan ſhe had founde <hi>Omnia probate,</hi> till ſhe was great with child, coulde not finde, <hi>Quod bonum eſt tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</hi> For (vnder correction, quoth he) though ye haue eloquently reherſed <hi>Catos</hi> tale, yet haue you not tolde the occaſion of the mattier, nor the ende that it came to: which if ye had done, ſhulde rather make againſt you, than with you. For whan <hi>Cato</hi> had ſated, as ye haue reherſed, <hi>Lucius Valeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:28147:4"/>
one of the Tribunes, aroſe and made anſwere. And ſo began he the oracion, that <hi>Valerius</hi> in that caſe had made. Addyng further, that the law <hi>Oppia</hi> was thervpon abrogate. Whiche was a playne profe (ſaied he) that the <hi>Senate</hi> allowed not <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos</hi> opinion.</p>
                  <p>Thus thei argued to and fro, till at length thei agreed, that all clenly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes were laufull vnto wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men, ſo longe as thei prouoked neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, nor vaine glorie: wherin thei ended the mattier for that tyme. Now this gentle woman reſtyng, not fully ſatiſfied with the once heryng of thoſe oracions, deſired maiſter Thomas of frendſhip, to ſende theim tranſlated vnto hir. Whiche he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to doe. And all be it, that he willed hir, to kepe it to hir ſelfe: yet ſhe thinkyng it ſuche a matter for the honeſt defence of women, as ought
<pb facs="tcp:28147:4"/>
not to be hidden, hath intreated me, thus to ſette it foorth, truſtyng to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify him wel enough, though he wold take it vnkindly. Willyng me beſides on hir behalfe, to beſeche you all (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reders) not to thinke ſhe hath done it of any purpoſe, to mainteine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe (whiche ſhe hir ſelfe naturally abhorreth) but euen ſimply for the pleaſaunt and well handlyng of the mattier: to ſtoppe their mouthes, that with raylyng on womens maners, ſeeme to procure theim ſelues a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:5"/>
                  <head>The letter ſent by may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Thomas to the gentle woman, with the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions that ſhe deſyred.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccordyng to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, I haue done my beſt in tranſlatyng as well <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> his oracion, alleged (by the man ye wote of) in diſprayſe of women, as alſo the other oracion, made by <hi>Lucius Valerius:</hi> whiche I recited for aunſwere to the ſame. And becauſe the law Oppia, mencioned in both thoſe oracions, is not plainely ſet foorth in <hi>Liuie,</hi> at the time of the makyng therof: I therefore haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ſuche priuate contribucions, as the Romayne people charged theim ſelfes withall about that tyme, to the intent, that beſides the argument of your matter, ye maie alſo vnderſtand the great kyndneſſe, that the people
<pb facs="tcp:28147:5"/>
at thoſe daies vſed towardes their common wealth. Whan almoſt euery man had rather peryſſhe priuately, than through his default the common wealth ſhould ſuſteine any preiudice. O, if we had no more but ſuche wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men now, as were than, I woulde thinke our worlde happie. But like as thei than had golden hertes, what ſo euer their apparayle was, ſo now (if I durſt ſpeake) I wolde ſaie, there bee many in golden apparayle, that haue ruſty hertes. And what of that? Should I therfore condemne you all? No no. If I had ben ſo muche your aduerſarie, I woulde neither in ſuche a matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er haue taken this peine, nor yet (whan it was) haue ſpoken as I did in mainteynyng your quarell.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe I ſaw you matched with one as rough as <hi>Cato,</hi> who not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with naturall reaſons, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined you ſo farre with ſcripture,
<pb facs="tcp:28147:6"/>
that ye ſhuld not be allowed to weare any pleaſant apparaile: me thought I coulde no leſſe in conſcience, but take your part. And though he moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in choler againſt you (as theſe men doe, that maie not be contraried) yet I truſt, in a mattier of ſuche weight, ye woll be well aduiſed ere ye folow his haſtie perſwaſion. God forbidde I ſhoulde pretende to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine you in pompe. For I know there is ſo little nede therof, that I wolde be ſorie ye ſhoulde not doe as ye liſt. But be it, or be it not, or be as it maie be: Sens ye required me ſo erneſtly to dooe this for you, now I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed my promiſe, I ſhall as her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily deſyre you to take it for a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my good will and frendeſhip: and in no wyſe to lette it paſſe your handes, leſt men ſhoulde thinke, with flatteryng you, I ſhoulde goe about
<pb facs="tcp:28147:6"/>
to mainteyne a thyng moſt neceſſary to be reſtreigned. Thus with my her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commendacions. &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your owne to commaunde William Thomas.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="notes_on_letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:7"/>
                  <head>The notes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples beneuolence promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in my letter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> warres, that about .MM. yeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe happened betwene the Romains and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginenſes, were ſo notable, as lightly the greatter haue not ben hearde of, as well for the puiſſance or greatneſſe of both thoſe common wealthes, as for the longe tyme of their obſtinate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencion. The circumſtances wherof are to be redde in <hi>Liuie,</hi> and other good authours, that haue written it at length. But to my purpoſe now, ye muſt vnderſtand, that <hi>Annibal</hi> (the notableſt enemie that euer the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines had) not longe before theſe matters, had diuers times ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen the Romaines in plaine battaile:
<pb facs="tcp:28147:7"/>
and had ſo beaten theim, that after their fall at <hi>Cannas,</hi> where a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful nombre as well of Senatours as others, were ſlayne, it was reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in Rome: whether it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them to abandon the citie, and euery man to ſhyft for hym ſelfe: or els to abyde the aduenture that the Goddes woulde ſende them. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly if <hi>Annibal</hi> after his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie had gone ſtreight to Rome, the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne aſtate had than finyſſhed his glorie. But whether his ſlackeneſſe gaue them courage: or their valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made theim deſperate: or that the ſterres had predeſtinate a greatter felicitie vnto theim: or what ſo euer the occaſion was, the Romaines per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuered, and by littell and littell ſo recouered, that at length they chaſed <hi>Annibal</hi> out of Italie, and ſendyng <hi>Scipio</hi> into Affrike, didde vnto Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage that, whiche <hi>Annibal</hi> myght
<pb facs="tcp:28147:8"/>
haue done to Rome, ſacked it, ſpoyled it, burned it, and rooted vp the verie foundacions. Neuertheleſſe ete thei coulde bryng this to paſſe, thei were many tymes in ſo great extremitees, that if the priuate perſons of Rome had not with their owne mainteined the publike charges, their thynges coulde neuer haue proſpered as they dyd.</p>
                  <p>¶For firſt whan <hi>Titus Sempronius,</hi> and <hi>Quintus Fabius Maximus,</hi> were conſules, the <hi>Scipios,</hi> that than had the gouernaunce of the armies in Spayne, wrote vnto Rome ſpecially for garmentes and vittailes: without the whiche thei coulde not mainteine the warres. And becauſe the tributes of <hi>Sicilia</hi> and <hi>Sardinia</hi> were ſcarſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to furniſhe the armies continuyng in thoſe countreis, and that there were ſo many Romaynes ſlayne at <hi>Traſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>menus</hi> and <hi>Cannas,</hi> that few
<pb facs="tcp:28147:8"/>
were left to paie any tribute at home. Therfore <hi>Fuluius</hi> the <hi>Pretor,</hi> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the people, that for as muche as the cuſtomers and fermours of the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenues of the common wealth, were become very ryche, as well of poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as of goodes, through the vſe of publike thynges: Therfore it was now neceſſary they ſhoulde bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreigned, with their ſubſtance to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour the common wealthes neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, in furniſhing the army of Spayne: to be paied agayne of the firſt money, that ſhoulde come to the Treaſorie. For the whiche the <hi>Pretor</hi> appointed a daie, that the people ſhoulde aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to determine. At whiche daie <hi>XIX.</hi> of thoſe cuſtomers and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours offered theim ſelues, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the whole prouiſion. So that the armie, for that tyme, was no leſſe furniſhed, by priuate men, than the common wealth woulde haue done, in
<pb facs="tcp:28147:9"/>
tyme of their moſt proſperitee.</p>
                  <p>¶Afterwardes, in the conſulate of <hi>Quintus Fabius Maximus,</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Marcellus,</hi> vpon the newes, that the Sicilians rebelled, and were in armes, whan <hi>Titus Octacilius</hi> ſhould be ſent with an armie thither: there wanted a nombre of mariners and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges to furnyſhe the nauie.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore a generall order was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that the Romaines, after certaine rates of their ſubſtaunce ſhoulde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide mariners at their owne charges, ſome one, ſome .iii. ſome .v. and ſome vii. paide for an whole yere. Whiche was the firſt time, that euer any Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne army was ſette foorth at the charges of the priuate citeſins.</p>
                  <p>¶An other tyme, whan the Treaſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was cleane without money, ſo that the <hi>Cenſoures</hi> had not, wherwith to repaire the temples: nor to geue the <hi>Curules</hi> their horſes, nor to doe ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:28147:9"/>
other thynges as apperteygued to their offices. The calamitee therof moued a nombre of thoſe, that ought to haue had money of them, contrary wiſe to come with money vnto them, exhortyng them to doe all thynges as liberally, as if the common wealth floriſſhed, promiſyng, not to demande repayment before the warres were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: like as the maſters, of whom the ſlaues were bought, refuſed to take their money before the ende of the warres. Whiche good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion beyng alſo founde in the people, moued the officers to take vp the goodes of the widowes and orphanes vpon credite, to be aunſwered of the common wealth: and ſo farre this good will increaſed, that the fame therof engendred ſo great a liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee emongeſt the ſouldiours in the campe, that no pryuate horſe manne, nor Centurion, woulde receyue his
<pb facs="tcp:28147:10"/>
paies, callyng theim <hi>Mercenarij</hi> that otherwiſe did.</p>
                  <p>¶But the laſt and moſt notable was, after the ſeuere ſentence geuen againſt the Capuans, perſwaded by the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of <hi>Marcus Attilius Regulus,</hi> the ambaſſadours, as well of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> as of Capua beyng than diſpatched, the Conſules tended to the appoinctment of the army, and that perfourmed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to treate of the furniture of their nauie. To the whiche, becauſe thei wanted as well mariners as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, thei commaunded euery priuate man, after his rate, to prouide mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and galey men: and to vittayle and paie them for <hi>.XXX.</hi> daies, as it had ben ſeene tofore. This procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion ſo muche ſterred mens hertes, that thei wanted rather capitaynes, than matter of rebellion, ſaiyng, that the Conſules, after the ruine of the Sicilians and Capuans, had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:28147:10"/>
alſo to deſtroie the romayne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whiche was alreadie conſumed by the tributes of ſo many yeres: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng nothyng left than but the bare lande ſpoyled by the warres: their ſlaues were all taken from theim, ſome to the feelde, and ſome to the ſea: And betwene the findyng of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, and paiyng of tributes, that little ſiluer and money that they had, was cleane ſpent. So that it was impoſſible to conſtreigne them, to geue that thei had not. Wherfore if they woulde ſell their goodes, thei might: and than coulde thei vſe no more cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltee but agaynſt their bodies, that onely reſted: whiche if they ſhoulde be compelled to redeeme, they coulde not, wantyng wherwith.</p>
                  <p>¶Theſe thinges were not ſpoken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, or ſecretely, but openly, and to the Conſules faces: the people aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyng by heapes together, whom
<pb facs="tcp:28147:11"/>
thei pacified as well as they coulde. Neuertheleſſe the next daie, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate beyng aſſembled, it was after longe diſputacion concluded, that whether it were right or wronge, this burdeine muſt needes be ſuſteined by priuate perſones, the Treaſourie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng vtterly without money. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man reſtyng as it were amaſed at the mattier, the Conſule <hi>Leuinus</hi> ſpake on this wiſe.</p>
                  <p>LIke as our office is aboue the Senate, and the Senatours ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours to the people in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: ſo ought we to be the chiefe and firſte of all other, to enterpriſe any great or weighty matter. For he that woll charge his inferiours with any greuous impoſicion, and firſt practiſe it in hym ſelfe, ſhall finde theim the better diſpoſed to obey, eſteemyng theyr charge the leſſe, whan they ſee their betters freely take the greatter
<pb facs="tcp:28147:11"/>
part of the burdein vpon them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the ende that the Romayne people be not diſapointed of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, that we intende to make, and that priuate men refuſe not to fynde the mariners: let vs commaunde as well our ſelues as all you that be Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, that to morow next we put all our golde and ſyluer, and out coyned braſſe in common, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuche wiſe as no man reteyne more to him ſelfe than his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ynges, his wiues, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes: and to his ſonne his table tis: and he that hath wyfe or doughters, one vnce of golde. And they that haue fitten, as magiſtrates, in the feate <hi>Curule,</hi> maie reſerue their horſes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimentes, and two poundes of ſiluer, to vſe in a ſalt and goblette for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice. The reſt of the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to haue but one pounde of ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and all other houſeholders to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue onely in maſſe money, 5000. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:28147:12"/>
a pece. All our other golde and ſiluer, and braſſe money, let vs imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately bryng vnto the .iii. magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the banke, without other deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacion of the Senate, to the ende that our voluntarie contribucion and vehement deſyre to the maintenance of our common wealth, maie fyrſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure the myndes of the chiualrie, and conſequentely of the people, to dooe the like. This onely waie we the Conſules haue founde after muche diſputacion, which with goddes helpe let vs take in hande. For as longe as we preſerue the aſtate of our common wealth: ſo longe we dooe mainteyne the ſuretie of our owne priuate thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Where as habandonyng the publike, we can kepe nothyng our owne. Wherevnto vniuerſally all their voyces were ſo agreable, that the Conſules beyng highly thanked, and the Senate diſſolued, euery man
<pb facs="tcp:28147:12"/>
applied him ſelfe with ſo muche haſt, to bryng in their golde, ſiluer, and money, that well was he, whiche in the regeſters myght bee wrytten e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the firſt, in ſuche wiſe, that neither the officers ſufficed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, nor the clerkes to write: which conformitie of the Senate, was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally folowed by the knightes, and conſequently by the people. So that without other commaundement or perſwaſion of the magiſtrates, the common Treaſourie was furniſſhed with money to make the paies, and the nauie ſufficiently equipped to the ſea. And ſo all thynges neceſſary for the warres beyng prouided, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſules departed towardes theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="Catos_oration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:13"/>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <head>T. L. Decad. 4. lib. 4.</head>
                     <p>EMonge the cares of the greatte warres, eyther yet ſcarſely fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, or like to continue, there happened a ſmall thyng to be ſpoken of, though neuertheleſſe it increaſed by parttakynges to great contencion. <hi>Marcus Fundanius,</hi> and <hi>Lucius Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerius</hi> tribunes, proponed vnto the people the abrogacion of the law cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Oppia.</hi> This law was ſet foorth by <hi>Caius Oppius,</hi> one of the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whan <hi>Quintus Fabius,</hi> and <hi>Titus Sempronius</hi> were Conſules, as the greatteſt heate of the punike war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> that no woman ſhoulde haue aboue halfe an ounce of golde in his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayle, nor weare garmentes wrought of diuers colours, nor ſhoulde ryde in chariottes in Rouſe or other towne, or within a myle of any of them, onleſſe it were to the open ſacrifices. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:28147:13"/>
and <hi>Publius Iunij Brutij</hi> lyke wyſe beeyng tribunes of the people, defended the law <hi>Oppia,</hi> ſaiyng: They woulde not ſuffre it to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled. And many noble men drew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſome to perſwade, and ſome to diſſwade the mattier. In ſo muche that the Capitoll was replenyſhed with a multitude of men, aduaunſyng and repugnyng this law. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones, neither for feare of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritee, nor for ſhame, nor yet for the commandement of theyr houſbandes coulde bee kept in: but fitted all the ſtretes of the citee, and kept the waies enteryng in to the high ſtrete, entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng all men as thei paſſed: that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng theyr common wealth floriſſhed, and euery mans priuate good fortune daiely increaſed, they wolde be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, that the matrones might alſo be reſtored vnto their auncient orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. This frequenſie of women
<pb facs="tcp:28147:14"/>
daiely increaſed. For the women of the townes and villages nere there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout reſorted to the citee, and toke on theim ſo muche courage, that they went to the Conſules, the Pretors, and the other magiſtrates, beſechyng theim to fauour their cauſe. But <hi>Marcus Porcius Cato</hi> was ſo extreme an aduerſarie agaynſt theyr deſyres, that for the maintenance of the law, whiche they ſought to abrogate, he made this oracion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="oration_proper">
                     <head>The oracion of <hi>Cato</hi> agaynſt womens libertee.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F euery one of you, O Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, had determined to haue preſerued the ryght and maieſtie of a huſbande ouer his owne wife, we ſhoulde now haue had leſſe buſineſſe with all theſe women together. But as our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee,
<pb facs="tcp:28147:14"/>
by our owne weakeneſſe is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the women in our owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: euen ſo here in the open ſtretes it is ouerthrowen and troden vnderfote. And becauſe we wolde not euery man particularly reſyſt his owne: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now we are abaſſhed to reſyſt them all together. In dede I thought it had ben but a fable feigned, that in a certayne Ilande all the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, by conſpiracie of the women, was vtterly deſtroied: but now I ſee, there is no kynde ſo ſmall, in whom conſiſteth not extreme perill, it thei be ſuffred to aſſemble, to deuiſe, and to haue ſecrete conſultacions. And I can ſcarſely in my mynde dyſcerne, whether be the worſe, the thyng it ſelfe, or the example, by whiche it is attempted. The one wherof apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth vnto vs Conſules and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates: and the other vnto you Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes. For whether the thyng pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned
<pb facs="tcp:28147:15"/>
bee conuenient, or not for the common wealth, it toucheth you, by whoſe voyces it muſt be determined. This ſturre of the women, whether it be growen of it ſelfe, or rayſed by you <hi>Marcus Fundanius</hi> and <hi>Lucius Valerius,</hi> ſens vndoubtedly the blame thereof apperteyneth vnto the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, I wotte not, vnto whom it is more reprocheable, vnto you the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes, or vnto vs the Conſules. To you, if ye haue allured the women to moue Tribuniciall ſedicions: And to vs, if we ſhalbe now conſtreigned to accept lawes by the compulcion of women, as we haue done here to fore by the common people. Treuly I came euen now through the middeſt of the women, not without bluſhyng. And if the reſpect of the maieſtee and ſhame faſtnes of euery of them apart, had not reteined me more than the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of theim al together (that they
<pb facs="tcp:28147:15"/>
ſhulde not ſeeme rebuked of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſule) I wolde haue ſaied: what new trycke is this? to renne abrode to ſtoppe the waies, and to intreate ſtrange men? Coulde not euery one of you haue deſyred this of hit owne at home? what, are you more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant abrode, than within the doores? and more of other mens, than of your huſbandes. For in deede if men can not of their owne ryght kepe their wiues within their due termes, it ſhal little auayle what lawes bee made or vnmade here. Our aunceſtours woulde not conſent, that women ſhoulde dyſpoſe any thyng though well it were their owne, without the authoritee of their ſuperiours: And therfore they were alwaies directed by their fathers, their bretherne, and their huſbandes. And we neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe (by goddes leaue) woll ſuffre theim to meddle with the rule of the
<pb facs="tcp:28147:16"/>
common wealth, to myngell theim ſelfes with vs in the open ſtrete, in the parliament, and in the Squit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines. For what els doe thei now in the ſtretes, and at the corners, but comfort, ſome to forder the Tribunes purpoſe, and ſome other, that the law maie be abrogate. Bridle (I ſaie) this arrogant ſexe, and theſe vntame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able beaſtes. For if ye doe not bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle theim now, neuer loke to bridle theim. This is the leaſt thyng, that offendeth the women of all the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that by the cuſtomes or lawes they are burdened, but they deſyre a libertee of all thynges, or rather to ſaie the trouth, a laſciuiouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p>For if thei preuaile in this, what woll they not attempt? Conſider all the lawes that concerne women, by the whiche our aunceſtours reſtreigned their libertee, makyng theim obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to their houſebandes: and whan
<pb facs="tcp:28147:16"/>
you haue all gathered, it is euident, ye can yet ſcarſely rule them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ye now ſuffre your wyues to reproue lawes, and thus by one and one to wreſt them out of your handes, and at length to make theim ſelfes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall vnto their huſbandes: thynke you than, ye ſhalbe hable to ſupport them? For whan thei are become your felowes: foorthwith thei woll bee your betters. By god, thei not onely refuſe to bee burdened with any new mattier, but alſo requiryng not the right thei offer a wronge: that a law, which by due order hath ben decreed, and with the vſe and experience of ſo many yeres allowed, ſhoulde now be annulled: Meanyng, with the abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatyng of one law to weaken the reſt. There is no law, that ſerueth to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans profite: but this ought to be regarged, whether it bee commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe for the greatter part and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.
<pb facs="tcp:28147:17"/>
For if euery man myght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale or condempne that part of the law, that priuately annoyeth hym ſelfe: what ſhulde it auayle the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre to make lawes? whan inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently they, agaynſt whom it were made, myght annull theim. I wolde fayne heare neuertheleſſe, for what cauſe the matrones ſhoulde royle foorth ſo amaſed, that ſcarſely they can forbeare the hygh ſtrete, or the counſayle houſe. Is it for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcion of their fathers, their houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes, their children, or their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne out of the handes of <hi>Annibal?</hi> There is no ſuche cauſe why. And god defend our common wealth ſhuld be in any ſuche neceſſitee. And yet whan it was ſo in deede, their pitious praiers were reiected. Perchaunce they wyll ſaie: neither pitee nor care for theyr owne, but religion onely hath drawen theim together to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:28147:17"/>
the mother <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Peſinunte,</hi> commyng out of Phrygia. O, what pretence or ſurmyſe maie be deuiſed to cloke the ſediciouſe aſſemble of theſe women? They maie ſaie, it is becauſe we wolde gliſter in golde and purple, that we maie ryde in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ottes through the citee both worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies and holydaies, triumphyng o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the law now ouercome and abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate: and ouer your ſuffrages taken and wreſted out of your handes: to the ende our ſumptuouſeneſſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe be not reſtreigned. You haue hearde me often complayne of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens ſuperfluouſe expences, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes of mens, not onely of the priuate, but alſo of magiſtrates: and that this citee is peſtred with two ſondry vices, Auarice and Prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee: whiche two peſtilences haue ben the ſubuerſion of all great empyres. For now the more that the good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb facs="tcp:28147:18"/>
of our common wealth dayly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, and that our Empyre is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, we beeyng entred into Greece and Aſia, countreis repleniſhed with al deliciouſe thyngꝭ: and that alſo we beginne to draw vnto vs the treaſures of kynges: the more doe I feare, leaſt thoſe thynges haue rather taken vs, than we theim. Theſe pictures and images brought hither from <hi>Siracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> are daungerous vnto this towne. Yea I here dyuers men ouermuche preyſe the ornamentes of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and of <hi>Athens,</hi> makyng theim as wonders, and laughyng theſe earthen goddes of the Romaines to ſcorne. But I had rather we ſhoulde ſtycke to theſe our fauourable goddes, as I truſt they will be, if we conſerue them in their places. In our fathers time kynge <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> by his ambaſſadour tempted not only the mindes of men, but alſo of women, with preſentes, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:28147:18"/>
euer the law <hi>Oppia</hi> was made to prohibite their exceſſe: and yet was there none that wolde receiue theim. And for what cauſe trow you? Euen for the ſame cauſe that our anceſtours had, not to thinke that euer any ſuche law ſhoulde nede to be made. For there was than none exceſſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred it. Yea like as it is neceſſarie, diſeaſes be fyrſt knowen er euer the remedies bee had: So euill deſyres are ſyredde er euer lawes be made to refourme theim. What was the cauſe that the law <hi>Licinia</hi> for fiue hundred acres of lande was made?<note place="margin">Law Licinia.</note> Was it any other, but the vnſaciable deſyre of men to ioygne lande vnto lande? And wherefore was the law <hi>Cincia,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Law Cincia,</note> of gyftes and preſentes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deigned? but becauſe the people than were beecome tributaries and vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalles vnto the Senatours. It was no meruayle, that neyther the law
<pb facs="tcp:28147:19"/>
                        <hi>Oppia,</hi> nor any other lyke was than made for the bridelyng of womens pompe, whan golde and purple be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng freely geuen and offred, coulde not be receyued. Mary if <hi>Cineas,</hi> with thoſe preſentes, ſhould now goe about the towne, he ſhoulde fynde them, that openly wold receiue them. And truely I can not imagen either the cauſe or the reaſon of ſome mens gredines. For like as the prohibityng of ſomewhat vnto one, whiche to an other is permitted, ſeemeth to bee grounded on ſome naturall ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, or vncomelyneſſe: Euen ſo, if all the apparayle of you women were of one ſort, wherof ſhoulde any of you feare to be noted? Truely the ſhame eyther of auarice or of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee is verie great: but the law clereth you of both, whan you haue not that, which is not lauful for you to weare. O, (ſaieth the ryche woman) I can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:28147:19"/>
awaie with this equalitee. Why ſhoulde not I be decked with golde and purple? And why ſhoulde other folkes pouertee bee hydde vnder the colour of this law? that wantyng the thynges they can not haue, it ſhoulde ſeme thei might haue them, if it were not prohibited. But will you Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes put this in ſtryfe emongeſt your wiues? that the riche ſhall haue that, whiche other maie not? And that the poore (becauſe they woulde not therfore be contempned) ſhall ſtrayne them ſelfes aboue their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? For ſeus thei beginne to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that that needeth not: at length thei ſhal not be aſhamed whan they nede. She that can prouide of hir ſelfe, maie doe it, but ſhe that can not, muſt craue of hir houſebande. And happie ſhall that houſebande be, that whether he be praied or not prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (if he geue not) ſhall ſee that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:28147:20"/>
by an other, that he hath not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him ſelfe. Euen now ye ſee, thei openly intreate other womens huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes, and more then that, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the law and the voyces: and through their importance doe of ſome opteine graunt, againſt him ſelfe, his goodes and children. For as ſoone as the law quayleth from bridelyng thy wifes exceſſe, loke thou no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to bridell hir. Nor beleue not (O, Romaynes) that euer the matter will returne vnto the aſtate it was in before the makyng of this law. For it were better, not to accuſe an euyll man, than to leaue him vnpunyſhed. And this exceſſe ſhuld haue ben more tollerable, if it had neuer ben ſpoken of, than it will be now, if ye breake theſe bandes. Like vnto the prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of a fierſe wylde beaſt, beyng lefte goe after he hath ben chafed in holde. Wherfore myne opinion is, ye
<pb facs="tcp:28147:20"/>
ſhoulde in no wyſe abrogate the law <hi>Oppia.</hi> Not withſtandyng I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche all the goddes to proſpere your determinacions, what ſo euer they ſhalbe.</p>
                     <p>After this, whan the Tribunes of the people, that had profeſſed alſo to interrupt this matter, had ſpoken ſomwhat to the ſame purpoſe, At the laſt <hi>Lucius Valerius,</hi> for the optey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the contrarie (by hym ſette foorth before) ſpake on this wiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="oration_in_response">
                     <head>The oracion of <hi>Lucius Valerius</hi> agaynſt <hi>Catos.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F priuate men onely had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand to perſwade or diſſwade that that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, I for my part, thinking there had ben enough ſaied on both ſides, wold with ſilence haue abidden your iudgementes. But now that ſo
<pb facs="tcp:28147:21"/>
graue a man, as the Conſule <hi>Marcus Portius,</hi> not onely with his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee (which though he had not ſpoken, had yet ben of great importaunce) but alſo with a longe exact and well han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled oracion hath impugned our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. I am conſtreigned, with a few woordes to anſwere hym, though he hath conſumed mo wordes in womens correction, than in diſſwadyng our purpoſe, and all to the ende, that he wolde bryng in doubt, whether the thyng by him reproued, proceded of the women voluntarily, or by our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement. Wherfore I ſhall defende the matter, but not our ſelfes: whom the Conſule hath burdeyned more in woordes than in deede. He calleth this companie of women, ſometyme a ſedicion, and ſometyme a rebellion: that the wiues, in the time of a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able floriſſhyng and fortunate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, ſhoulde openly deſyre
<pb facs="tcp:28147:21"/>
the abrogacion of a law, made againſt theim in the terrible ſharpe tyme of warres. I know, that to aggrauate the matter, both theſe and other ſuch woordes are gathered. And we all know <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> to be, not onely a graue oratour, but alſo ſometyme ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bitter: not withſtandyng that he is gentill of nature. But for all that, what noueltee haue theſe wyues at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted in commyng by companies abrode to purſue their owne cauſe? Came they neuer abrode before? I will turne ouer thyne owne bokes of Originalles againſt the, and ſee there, how often tymes thei haue done this, and all to the profyte of the common wealth. And to beginne, Firſt whan <hi>Romulus</hi> reigned, the Capitoll beyng already taken by the <hi>Sabines,</hi> and thei feightyng with baners diſplaied in the middeſt of the high ſtrete: was not the battaile ſtaied by the womens
<pb facs="tcp:28147:22"/>
rennyng betweene both armies? And after the expulſion of kynges, whan the army of the <hi>Volſci</hi> were incam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped within fiue myles of this towne, vnder the leadyng of <hi>Marcus Corio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus,</hi> did not the women turne backe that army, that els had deſtroied this citee? And whan this towne was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the frenche men, dyd not the matroues of theyr owne free will, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly geue the golde, wherwith the citee was redeemed? Yea and (to paſſe ouer theſe antiquities) euen in the laſt warres, whan moſt neede of money was, dyd not the widowes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Treaſoury with their owne money? And whan the new goddes were fet home to helpe vs in our great neede, went not the matrones to the ſea ſyde, to receiue the mother of the goddes? He will perchaunce ſaie, the cauſes are not lyke. In dede I meane not to compare the cauſes together.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:28147:22"/>For it ſuffiſeth me to proue this no new thyng. And where in thynges indifferently belongyng as well to men as to women, no man hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at theyr comyng abrode: why doe we now meruayle, they ſhoulde ſo dooe in a matter of their owne? And what (I praie you) haue they done? Helas we are verie hearde of hearyng: if whan maiſters diſdeigne not to heare the requeſtes of theyr ſlaues, we ſhall refuſe to here our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt wiues. But now to come to the matter, wherin the Conſules oracion tendeth vnto two pointes. Firſt, it ſhal be againſt his wil, that any law ſhuld be abrogate: and ſpecially, that a law, whiche concerneth the reſtreinct of womens exceſſe, ſhulde be annulled. So that the fyrſt part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſules oracion ſeemeth a common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of all lawes: and the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt ſuperfluitee, ſeemeth agreable
<pb facs="tcp:28147:23"/>
to his ſeuere cuſtomes. Wherfore it I allege not the vanitee that is in both theſe poyntes, it were to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leſt ſome of you myght be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to an errour. For like as I confeſſe, that none of thoſe lawes, whiche were made, not of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitee of a certayne tyme, but for the perpetuall profite to endure for euer, ought in no wiſe to be annihilate: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be ſuche, as eyther experience condemneth, or ſome ſtate of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth declareth to be vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Euen ſo doe I ſee thoſe lawes that ſpeciall tyme hath ben the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of, to bee mortall (if I maie ſo call them) and mutable as tymes are. For thoſe that are made in peace, the warre many tymes doth breake: and the peace likewiſe them that are made in warre. As in guidyng of a ſhippe, the caulme requyreth one thyng, and the ſtorme an other. So that theſe
<pb facs="tcp:28147:23"/>
thynges beyng of diuerſe natures, I wolde know, of whether kinde thinke you this law to be, that we doe abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate? Is it one of thoſe auncient kyngely lawes, made at the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of this towne? Or (in the ſecond degree) is it any of them, written in the <hi>.XII.</hi> tables by the <hi>.X.</hi> men, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preſcribe lawes? without the whiche (beecauſe our auncetours thought the honour of women not poſſible to bee conſerued) we alſo ſhoulde feare, that with the breakyng hereof the ſhamefaſtneſſe and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our wyues ſhoulde periſſhe? Who knoweth not this to bee a new law, made <hi>.XX.</hi> yere agoe, in the time of <hi>Quintus Fabius</hi> and <hi>Titus Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pronius</hi> Conſules, without the which the matrones, hauyng liued ſo many yeres with excellent cuſtomes: why ſhould it be feared, vpon the takyng awaie of this law, that thei ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:28147:24"/>
fall to ſo diſordinate expenſes? In deede, if this law had ben made to bridell the exceſſe of women, it might bee ſuſpected, that the breche of it might reuoke their laſciuiouſeneſſe. But why it was made, the tyme it ſelfe doth well declare. <hi>Annibal</hi> in Italy had wonne the battaile at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> and hauyng gotten <hi>Tarentum, Arpos,</hi> and <hi>Capua,</hi> it ſeemed he was commyng with his armie to Rome, Our ſubiectes rebelled. There were no ſouldiours to furniſhe the armie. None to defende the nauie. No mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the Treaſoury. The ſlaues were bought to arme the galeis, on condicion their maiſters ſhoulde bee paied for them after the warre. At the ſelfe ſame tyme, corne, and all other thynges, that the warre required, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng lackyng, the publicanes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toke the prouyſion. We paied out gallie ſlaues of our owne purſes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:28147:24"/>
man after the rate of his taxyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we gaue al our gold and ſyluer to the publike, the Senatours being the firſt that beganne ſo to do. The widowes and orphanes brought theyr money to the Treaſoury, and a certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porcion was preſcribed: aboue the rate wherof, no perſone might kepe in his houſe, golde or ſyluer, or any coyned money of ſyluer or braſſe. It is much like, that the matrones ſhuld be than ſo decked with ornamentes and exceſſe, that the law <hi>Oppia</hi> was neceſſary to bridell them. Whan (the ſacrifice of Ceres beyng deferred, and the matrones all occupied in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng) the Senatours commaunded theim to ceaſe their doule, within <hi>XXX.</hi> daies. Who knoweth not, that becauſe it was requiſite, all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate money ſhoulde bee conuerted to the publike vſe, that the very pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee and miſerie of the citee hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:28147:25"/>
this law to continue ſo longe as the cauſe, wherfore it was made, ſhuld endure? For it thoſe thynges ſhoulde be obſerued for euer, that by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate was decreed, are by the people commaunded through the neceſſitee of that tyme: why doe we repaie money to priuate men? why doe we pledge our publike reuenues for preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? why dooe we not bie ſlaues to ſende into the warres? why dooe not we that be priuate, fynde galey men, as we dyd than? All other degrees, and all men doe feele the amendement of our aſtate: our wyues onely ſhall not atteygne the fruite of our publike peace and proſperitee? we men weare purple embrodered, beyng magiſtrates and prieſtes: and our ſonnes like wiſe weare gownes of purple garded: the like wherof is permitted vnto the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of our Colonies, and to our burgeſes enfrauncheſed: as here in
<pb facs="tcp:28147:25"/>
Rome the baſeſt ſort of magiſtrates, euen the ſtrete maiſters, haue theyr gownes garded. and not the quycke onely haue this preheminence, but the dead alſo may be burnt in purple: and ſhall we kepe the vſe thereof onely from our wiues? And beyng laufull for the that art a man, to haue purple in the coueryng of thy bed: wilt thou not ſuffre the mother of thy houſe to weare a garment therof? Shall thy horſe bee better apparayled than thy wyfe? Mary in purple, which wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and will conſume, (though not rightfull) yet I ſee ſome cauſe of ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng: but in golde, wherin beſide the workemanſhyp, can be no loſſe, what euill can there be? But rather a ſtore beneficiall, as well to the publike as to the priuate behofe, proued by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience? He ſaieth, that whan the women haue it not, there can bee no priuate enuie betwene theim. But
<pb facs="tcp:28147:26"/>
truely they are all in ſorow and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, to ſee thoſe ornamentes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto the wiues of our ſubiectes the latines, which are prohibited vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne: and ſeeyng thoſe decked with golde and purple, ride about the towne, and them ſelfes folow a foote, as though the empyre were in their citees, and not in ours. Such thynges are enough to ſterre mens hertes: and what trow you than it will doe vnto ſimple women, whiche will be moued with a little? Thei haue no part, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in magiſtrates, nor in prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod, nor in triumphes, nor in armes, nor in guyftes, nor in the ſpoyles of warre. The onely glory of women is their clenlines, their ornamentes and apparayle: wherein thei reioyce and triumph. Which thynges our aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours called the womens worlde. And what other thyng can they leaue of whan they mourne, but purple and
<pb facs="tcp:28147:26"/>
gold? Or whan thei leaue mournyng<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what els can thei take againe? In the time of reioyſyng, or of ſupplicacions, what can they adde but their better apparaile? what though the law <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia</hi> were abrogate, ſhould it no more be in your powers, to forbidde your doughters, your wiues, your ſiſters, and as many as be vnder your rule, the thynges that the law now forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth? The women will neuer thinke them ſelfes ridde out of ſeruitude, as longe as ye kepe their dereſt thynges from them. And thei abhorre that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertee, that is like vnto widowhead, or the death of their parentes or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Thei had rather the rule of their apparayle were in your power, than in the lawes. And you ought to haue them in your protection and defence, and not in ſeruitude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ye might ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther be called fathers or houſbandes, than maſters. The Conſule euen now
<pb facs="tcp:28147:27"/>
vſed greuouſe termes, callyng this the womens ſedicion and rebellion: as though it were to be feared, they ſhould take the holy hill or the Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine vpon them, as the obſtinate peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſomtime did. Neuertheleſſe, what ſo euer ye ſhal determine: thei ſimple ſoules muſt abide it. Wherfore the greatter your power is, ſo muche the more temperately ought ye to vſe it. ¶Theſe thynges beyng ſpoken both with and agaynſt the law: the next daie the nombres of women encreaſed abrode, and all in a flocke beſette the dores of the <hi>Brutij,</hi> whiche were the Tribunes, that reſiſted the purpoſe of their Colleagues: and wolde not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part thenſe, till theſe Tribunes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lented vnto theim. Whervpon there reſted no more doubt, but that all the Tribes wolde abrogate the law. So that <hi>.XX.</hi> yeres after it was made, it was annulled.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="glossary">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:27"/>
                  <head>A table of ſuche wordes as the reder ſmally ſkilled, ſhall not well perceiue.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Sſes, cometh of as, aſſis, a ſmall coyne amonge the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes .x. of them dyd coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trevayle our ſterlyng grote. fiue thouſande amounteth to viii. li. vi. <abbr>s.</abbr> viii. <abbr>d.</abbr> ſterlyng.</p>
                  <p>Auentinus, an hill at Rome.</p>
                  <p>Banke, is the place of exchange, or takyng of money vpon intereſt.</p>
                  <p>Capitoll, was the fortreſſe and chiefe place of Rome, where the Senate aſſembled in councell.</p>
                  <p>Conſules, were two chiefe officers of the citee of Rome, whiche were choſen euery yere, and bare hygheſt authoritee in the common wealth.</p>
                  <p>Cenſor, a iudge of mens maners. Alſo ſuch one as was appoynted to value mens goodes.</p>
                  <p>Colonies were certaine nombres of people ſent out of Rome to inhabite the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis conquered by theim.</p>
                  <p>Curules, were little cartes or dreies, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng in theim chaiers of yuory, wherin there ſatte certayne officers, whiche had the charge and ouerſyght of the buildyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges in Rome: ſometyme it is vſed for
<pb facs="tcp:28147:28"/>
the ſame officers.</p>
                  <p>Holy hill, whan the people rebelled againſt their rulers, they toke thoſe places for their ſtrength: and kept them till they had their willes.</p>
                  <p>Idea, the mother of the goddes.</p>
                  <p>Mercenarii, hyred ſouldiours.</p>
                  <p>Matrones, were the citeſyns wyues of Rome.</p>
                  <p>Martius Coriolanus, a noble Romayne, who beyng vnkyndely exiled out of his countrey, prouoked a people cald Volſci to warre againſt them: and woulde by no meane be pacified: but by the onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie of his mother, that made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from his enterpriſe.</p>
                  <p>Pretor, in the olde tyme was euery officer, that had the rule of any army. Afterward he that had iudicial authoritee, as it were the chiefe iudge, and had other iudges ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng vnder him.</p>
                  <p>Phrygia, a realme in Aſia the leſſe.</p>
                  <p>Pyrrhus, a king of Epyre, that made warre to the Romaynes.</p>
                  <p>Publicanes, were certayne fermours that toke the cuſtomes and other publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues in fee ferme.</p>
                  <p>Publike, is as much to ſay, as the common.</p>
                  <p>Punike warres, were the warres betwene the Carthaginenſes and the Romaynes.</p>
                  <p>Siracuſa, a notable citee in Sicilia, called at this daie Sarragoſe.</p>
                  <p>Sabines were a people dwellyng neere
<pb facs="tcp:28147:28"/>
Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ynes (hauyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>) raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for enci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cion.</p>
                  <p>Suffrages, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſembled, in geuyng their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſent.</p>
                  <p>Tribunes, were certayne officers ordeyned as proctours for the common people to mainteyne the peoples libertee.</p>
                  <p>Tribuniciall ſedicion, ſedicion ſturred vp by the Tribunes in the behalfe of the people.</p>
                  <p>Tribe, a warde, a part of the people, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme diuided in three partes.</p>
                  <p>Volſci, were a people of Italie, enemies to the Romaines.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS TABVLAE.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:28147:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>JMPRINTED AT</hi> London in Fleteſtrete, in the houſe of Thomas Birthelet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="lat">
            <body>
               <div type="Psalter_fragment">
                  <div n="137" type="Psalm">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:28147:1"/>
                     <p n="4">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>erunt <choice>
                           <abbr>om<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ia</abbr>
                           <expan>omnia</expan>
                        </choice> u<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:aber"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>er</ex>
                        </expan>ba oriſ tui·</p>
                     <p n="5">Et cantent in uiis <choice>
                           <abbr>dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i</abbr>
                           <expan>domini</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m</abbr>
                           <expan>quoniam</expan>
                        </choice> magna eſt <choice>
                           <abbr>gła</abbr>
                           <expan>gloria</expan>
                        </choice> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i</abbr>
                           <expan>domini</expan>
                        </choice>·</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Qm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           </abbr>
                           <expan>Quoniam</expan>
                        </choice> excelſus <choice>
                           <abbr>dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</abbr>
                           <expan>dominus</expan>
                        </choice> &amp; humilia reſpicit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; alta a longe
cognoſcit.</p>
                     <p n="7">Si ambulauero in medio <choice>
                           <abbr>t<hi rend="sup">i</hi>bulationis</abbr>
                           <expan>tribulationis</expan>
                        </choice> 
                        <unclear>uiuificabis</unclear>
me<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; ſuꝑ iram inimico<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>rum</ex>
                        </expan> meo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>rum</ex>
                        </expan> extendisti <unclear>manum</unclear>
tuam· &amp; ſaluum me fecit dextera tua.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</abbr>
                           <expan>Dominus</expan>
                        </choice> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>ret<hi rend="sup">i</hi>buet</abbr>
                           <expan>retribuet</expan>
                        </choice> ꝓ me<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</abbr>
                           <expan>domine</expan>
                        </choice> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>misc<g ref="char:dhook">d̔</g>ia</abbr>
                           <expan>misericordia</expan>
                        </choice> tua in <choice>
                           <abbr>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>m</abbr>
                           <expan>saeculum</expan>
                        </choice> 
                        <unclear>oꝑa</unclear>
manuum tuarum ne deſpicias.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="138" type="Psalm">
                     <p n="1-2">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>n<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</abbr>
                           <expan>Domine</expan>
                        </choice> ꝓbasti me &amp; cognouiſti me<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> tu <unclear>cognouisti</unclear>
ſeſſionem meam &amp; reſurrectionem <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">Intellexiſti cogitationes meas de <unclear>longe</unclear>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <unclear>ſemitam</unclear>
meam &amp; funiculum meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inueſtigasti<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">Et <choice>
                           <abbr>om<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es</abbr>
                           <expan>omnes</expan>
                        </choice> uias meas preuideſti<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <unclear>quia non eſt ſermo</unclear>
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:28147:29"/>
                     <p n="5">
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> eſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ex me<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
&amp; non potero ad eam.</p>
                     <p n="7">Quo ibo a <choice>
                           <abbr>ſp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu</abbr>
                           <expan>spiritu</expan>
                        </choice> tuo? &amp; quo a facie tuo fug<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">Si aſcendero in celum tu illic es<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>fernum ades·</p>
                     <p n="9">Si ſumpſero pennas meas <unclear>dilucolo</unclear>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:punctel"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>punctel</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
in extremis maris·</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
